[SPEAKER_00]: This is the Wisdom Podcast.
[SPEAKER_00]: Khyentse Rinpoche and Kamapa, when they meet, they will spend the whole day together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Talking about past histories.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even sometimes talk about ghosts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes Khyentse Rinpoche goes there and stay the whole day, have lunch together.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then sometimes they don't finish their conversation when Khyentse Rinpoche goes back to his bedroom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Khyentse Rinpoche would follow him and come to the bedroom and continue the story.
[SPEAKER_01]: Welcome to the Wisdom Podcast.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm Daniel Akin, CEO and publisher of Wisdom Publications.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before we get started, I wanted to tell you all about an exciting new initiative, the Wisdom Experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the Wisdom Experience, you'll find our full library of podcast episodes, and by subscribing, you'll have access to the video versions of some of our podcasts too.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can also gain access to our extensive online reading catalog, acclaimed lecture series, and many online courses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply go to wisdomexperience.org to check it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: For this episode of the Wisdom Podcast, I traveled to New York, where I had the great honor of speaking with Sheshan Rabjan Rinpoche, grandson and spiritual heir of the great Tibetan master, Dilgo Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: In this truly inspiring conversation, Rinpoche shares the most amazing stories about his close relationship with his grandfather, who was both his teacher and mentor for 20 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: He speaks about Dingo Kiense's remarkable qualities, his uncanny insight and intuition, astounding generosity, and his non-sectarian approach as a teacher across multiple traditions.
[SPEAKER_01]: I also asked Rinpoche about the history of the Sheshen lineage, as well as his own goals as both Dharma heir and teacher, and how he seeks to transmit the lineage in Tibet especially.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lastly, we discussed the topic of devotion, as well as the topic of mindfulness in mainstream culture.
[SPEAKER_01]: I hope you enjoy the conversation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were Khyentse Rinpoche's daughter's son.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you were recognized as a Rinpoche when you were quite young?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I was recognized as the seventh Shicheng Rinpoche reincarnation by his own 16 Karmapa together with Tengu Chen's Rinpoche and I think Choling Rinpoche, Chojolingpa, the father of Tukwudzhi Dabja.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the three together, of course mainly His Holiness Karmapa did the recognising and enthronement ceremony.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they said it was done very elaborate.
[SPEAKER_00]: After the ceremony, three days of the Tibetan Opera dance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Big celebration in Roopdeg.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think mainly because His Holiness Karmapa and His Holiness the Okhyentse Rinpoche were very very close.
[SPEAKER_00]: and Karmapa really loved Khyentse Rinpoche very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I heard a story once that Khyentse Rinpoche, just normal sort of conversation with his only 16 Karmapa,
[SPEAKER_00]: that what do you think happened to the masters in Tibet, because at that time there was no communication inside Tibet and outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they were going through different teachers.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Khyentse Rinpoche talked about, what do you think what happened to my teachers from Shechen, Ram Jam and Khyentse.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I heard them come up and said, you don't have to look for them, they are looking for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that was maybe much way before I was born.
[SPEAKER_01]: So His Holiness is like predicting that you are coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to look for, you don't have to look for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sounds like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: His Holiness 16 Kamabu was quite amazing with being able to, you know, recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that time most of the, of course, Khajiit and Nyingma and even Sakyah tradition, all the Turku's are recognized by, most of them recognized by him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your enthronement was where?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where was what?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually first, my grandmother was not so for Tulku, me being Tulku.
[SPEAKER_00]: She says, now these days, it's very difficult to raise Tulku.
[SPEAKER_00]: So better not name, give such a big name to my nephew.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't, grandson, I don't know what it will turn out to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I think after Karmapa and Khyentse Rinpoche confirmed, I think Khyentse Rinpoche had to pursue his own 16 Karmapa to sort of order my grandmother that I should be enthroned as a Turku.
[SPEAKER_00]: So of course, since my grandmother saw this, greatly respect to 16 Karmapa.
[SPEAKER_00]: So when 16 Karmapa says, okay, you must make him Turku, so she couldn't refuse.
[SPEAKER_00]: No choice there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then my enthronement was done in Rumthik Monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was so lucky that His Holiness Karmapa himself was there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I believe Thangur Rinpoche did the mandala, one of the mandala offering, and I think Tengah Rinpoche did one of the.
[SPEAKER_00]: So those two senior masters were there to do the, what do you call, part of the ceremony.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Khyentse Rinpoche was there, and Chogyo Lingpa...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't remember.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't remember him.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when they were discussing about recognizing Chogyo Rinpoche was there, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then what happens to you once you're enthroned?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you placed in the care of Khyentse Rinpoche or are you placed in the care of some… I think normally what happens is I was recognized in the Rumtek and I was, how do you say, admitted to a Rumtek monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: You sort of have to register under the Rumtek monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: and the His Holiness the 16th Karmapa appoint one Roomthik monk to be my kind of attendant or caretaker But I never stayed in Roomthik I always travelled with Khyentse Rinpoche and every year we go at least once a year to see His Holiness the 16th Karmapa When His Holiness the 16th Karmapa is alive Khyentse Rinpoche goes every year to see His Holiness the 16th Karmapa and he goes to Sikkim where the previous Donsay Khyentse's stupa So that's kind of yearly visit
[SPEAKER_00]: So every year I go and visit.
[SPEAKER_00]: His songs come up at that time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so do you remember those visits?
[SPEAKER_00]: A few things, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, like, Khyentse Rinpoche and Karmapa, when they meet, they will spend the whole day together, talking about past histories, and even sometimes talk about ghosts, and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they would spend the whole day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, sometimes, like, Khyentse Rinpoche goes there and stay the whole day, have lunch together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Karmapa would sit on the chair, kind of, there was like a sofa, and Khyentse Rinpoche would sit on the floor.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the whole day they talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: And no matter how many people visit, they just, people come and visit and go, but they just sit together.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then sometimes they don't finish their conversation when Khyentse Rinpoche goes back to his bedroom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sixteen Kamapa would follow him and come to the bedroom and continue the story.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's so nice to hear about these great masters and their friendships.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sometimes early morning, before even I'm up, I'm still in the bed.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I wake up, they already start talking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I have to pretend I'm sleeping still.
[SPEAKER_00]: So sometimes it would take a long time.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was sweating in my, what do you call it, bedding?
[SPEAKER_00]: My blanket.
[SPEAKER_01]: What amazing memories.
[SPEAKER_01]: What was the connection between His Holiness and Khyentse Rinpoche?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, firstly, I think also we are a little bit related, family-wise, because Karmapa is from Adu and Khyentse Rinpoche is Dingo.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just across the river, the two families settled in eastern Tibet, there again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, of course, Khyentse Rinpoche is very devoted to his own existing Karmapa.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they are very close, I think, from Tibet, from Surabaya itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they have that, from back in Tibet, their families were close.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I don't know how, in Kham itself, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think he was born in Kham, but then he was taken to Surabhu.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then much later, when Khyentse Rinpoche came to, I think, Tibet to pilgrimage, just before he left, then I think he spent a lot of time in Surabhu, Surabhu monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so you would travel with Kensei Rinpoche throughout the year and then come back to Rumtek?
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't actually stay in Rumtek?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I didn't stay.
[SPEAKER_00]: When Kensei Rinpoche comes, I go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I was traveling with Kensei Rinpoche since I was five.
[SPEAKER_00]: So wherever he went at that time, I came to America in 1976 or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And wherever he went, I was always with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So did you have to go to Shedra or something like that?
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't go to Shedra.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wanted to go to Shedra very much when I was young because some of my friends, turkus, they went to Shedra.
[SPEAKER_00]: After his solanus, he didn't come up and passed away.
[SPEAKER_00]: They started the first shedha in Rumtek Monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: So at that time they wanted me to stay because I was part of the Rumtek Tulku.
[SPEAKER_00]: They considered me as part of Rumtek Tulku.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then Khyentse Rinpoche said, no, just come with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just come with me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, come with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Second time was with Mysore, when Vendram Rinpoche has started the Nyingma Shedra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Vendram Rinpoche went there a few times to give teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that time, I really wanted to stay and study there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Namdraling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Namdraling, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Vendram Rinpoche said, okay, go with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: No need to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then another time,
[SPEAKER_00]: My friend, other Tulkus, like Jimei Kensei Rinpoche, Namkini Mbu, they are all going to Zongshan Shedra.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Khenpo Khingomangshun just arrived from Tibet.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they are all going there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I told Rinpoche, maybe I want to go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rinpoche said, no need to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So three times.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think Khyentse Rinpoche refused.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even some other lamas like Tukwudzin Tobja and these people, they thought that I should go to Shedra.
[SPEAKER_00]: So at one point, I think Tukwudzin Tobja, they said we must send Ramjam, young Ramjam to Shedra because he's always with Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't have much time to do the philosophical study.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I think to Bama Wangyal, pursue Ujjain Dabja to talk with Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Ujjain Dabja, he told me the story.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said he told Rinpoche and Rinpoche didn't like very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Rinpoche asked him, Ujjain Dabja, do you think there is someone who can teach more than what I can teach?
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then Ujjain Dabja, he kept quiet.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think no debater in the world could answer that question.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I didn't have the chance to go to Shedra.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't have much.
[SPEAKER_00]: But whenever the Khenpo's and teachers come to Khenpo Rinpoche's, I always try to receive some teachings.
[SPEAKER_00]: and a few things like that from different campos.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course I didn't go a very deep study, but I just received some basic kind of instructions on those different subjects of philosophy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So your education was just around being with Rinpoche and watching Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did Rinpoche teach you formally, like in classes, or does he mainly just give you lungs and show you rituals?
[SPEAKER_01]: How was it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, with Rinpoche, I think every evening there is one class, mostly by Jigme Lingpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: He went through the Tendakalarambha's commentary and that he went very thoroughly and we have recording also.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that I think he taught me maybe like three times.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then also the Shingtan Namyee, the more elaborate commentary.
[SPEAKER_00]: By Jimi Limbaugh.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that also he taught.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then also like Domsum Namyee.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So all those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have like evening class every day.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then I imagine Rinpoche is very busy as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has many responsibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: And one thing I was wondering, because Rinpoche did so many amazing things in his life and you got to see this in action.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the West here, we say we're so busy, we're so busy, but we really don't accomplish too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so I was wondering how Rinpoche, you know, went about his day.
[SPEAKER_01]: How was he able to do so much and care for so many people?
[SPEAKER_00]: That was quite interesting because we never felt with Rinpoche he is so busy We never felt he is busy because he always have a time somehow So no matter what like even like during Druk Chin's he would whole day he would sit in Druk Chin and during some time during the recitation he would compose his
[SPEAKER_00]: whatever he is composing, some of it is revealing his dharma, or sometimes he is composing commentaries on other dharma.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you look in his collection of works, he really worked so hard on other dharmas, which is not finished.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would complete the other dharmas, more than his own dharma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then same time he would give teachings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So many teachings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even sometime like 15 minutes bathroom break, he would start teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sitting on the throne, students standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And somehow we never felt that kind of busy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somehow there's always something going on, but you never felt that which doesn't have time.
[SPEAKER_00]: He always had a time for whatever he's doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And last time we had a meeting with younger Tulkus who were a little bit close with Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we sort of tried to recollect the memories of when Khyentse Rinpoche was giving teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one day we sort of put down all the teaching he gave in one day.
[SPEAKER_00]: We found out that he gave 13 different classes in one day.
[SPEAKER_00]: while he was giving the Tripitaka Transmission in Central Bhutan Now one of my friend, Drukku, Namni Rinpoche he had a very good recollecting memory He even remembers the different texts and who are the people who were receiving the teaching that time It was quite amazing that he would give 13 different teachings On top of that, he was giving the half-day transmission of the Tripitaka So somehow everything would fit into his schedule
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like Rinpoche had control over time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Almost like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels like Rinpoche, it seems what you're saying is always was graceful, never like rushing and busy in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, always have a time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so how did he manage his day?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was there some sort of rhythm to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like how does someone do so much and accomplish so much but yet be so graceful and feel like there's so much time?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: A few years ago I went to Switzerland and there was this, he's Khenzid Rinpoche's nephew, not very, very close, but some kind of grandson of his relative like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I was just talking with him and he said, oh, I have a letter from Khenzid Rinpoche when he went to Switzerland.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I said, oh, I'd like to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he bring me one whole file of letter, mostly Khenzid Rinpoche's own handwriting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he's not the most important student that Khenpo Rinpoche has.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just kind of far relative, distance relative.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then if you read the letter, it's just basic thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I hope you're doing well.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going here and there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, please keep on doing whatever you're doing, doing well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rinpoche felt that since he went to Switzerland from India, he might feel lonely.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we were very surprised because Rinpoche had so much time even to send that many letters without having a secretary, without having email and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all handwritten, posted to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somehow Rinpoche always had a time, no matter who you are, important or far relative or simple practitioner, somehow he would always give.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also he would somehow make you feel that you are the most important person that he met in that holiday.
[SPEAKER_00]: That much kind of attention he would give.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he was a special person.
[SPEAKER_01]: So not just so much time to do meaningful things, he had so much time for so many people, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Seems like that, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I also heard that Rinpoche's, someone mentioned, I can't remember who, but they were saying that Rinpoche had some, like just the simplest things, like Rinpoche's bow or Rinpoche's mouth would seem so special that it had some sort of like, you know, did you notice anything?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, did you have that feeling that the things around Rinpoche felt special as well?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the things that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, like his bowl, like ordinary things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't remember who said this, but I remember it stuck in my mind that someone said, even the ordinary things like Rinpoche's cup would feel so special.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm wondering if you felt like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I think the students, they feel, I think, very precious because it somehow brings back the memory.
[SPEAKER_00]: So Rinpoche had a lot of toys on his table.
[SPEAKER_00]: Toys?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, kind of like miniature people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Miniature animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rinpoche actually liked kind of rabbit because his name is Rapsaldhawa, brilliant moon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And somehow the Tibetans think that there is a shape of rabbit in the moon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somehow the rabbit is connected with his name.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I think some people must have given him a small rabbit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he kept it on the table.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then all the people thought, oh, he likes this kind of miniature animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: People started giving him.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he would just keep them on the table.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there are so many things like some are made out of crystal, some are just simple porcelain kind of animal, things like that that was just kept on his table.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so Rinpoche would keep these in front of him?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, just around the table like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there used to be three Indian sadhus, one with a turban and one with a bald head and one, there's another one, I don't remember, but Rinpoche used to point the bald head and say, this is Matthew.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is Matthew!
[SPEAKER_01]: So even like the most...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, you know, people have so much devotion for Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: They see he likes these things they want to offer for Rinpoche or they see his camp and they think it's so special.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I want to talk a little bit about devotion and...
[SPEAKER_01]: You spent so much time with Rinpoche and your life was around serving Rinpoche and then even now still serving Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I was hoping you could talk a little bit about devotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also, many students in the West are confused about what devotion is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was wondering if you could speak about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, since I was five, I was with Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, of course, I don't know what devotion is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And being with him and his kindness and his very kind kind of like beginning, I have feeling like he's my grandfather, very kind grandfather.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then slowly, slowly, it sort of changed towards devotion, faith and devotion.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think devotion is like complete trust.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Khyentse Rinpoche is someone like, from a relative level, from our perspective, he is someone like, if you give him 100% trust, he will take care of you 100%.
[SPEAKER_00]: Relative or spiritually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Worldly or spiritually, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even some people have a... Those days, like example in Bhutan, there's some restriction for travelling Tibetan refugees across Bhutan.
[SPEAKER_00]: People would come to us, Rinpoche, just to write a small letter to the police saying that,
[SPEAKER_00]: Let him go to Thimphu from Paro.
[SPEAKER_00]: So many people have received.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes he is like an immigration officer.
[SPEAKER_00]: He is an immigration officer, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that, he would take a time and like to say, oh, this is my disciple.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let him through the checkpost.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, in Bhutan, everybody knows Khyentse Rinpoche, so they would respect him, let the people go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somehow, if you have fully trust in him, he would sort of take care of everything, look after you and everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But of course, he will not impose you to receive some, you know, if you are not fully, if he doesn't, if you're not fully like 100%.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're fully 100% devoted to him and he knows that you are like...
[SPEAKER_00]: He is one of the close students.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then he would even decide.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would even tell you what empowerment, what teachings that you should receive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was quite an interesting incident with one of the Rinpoche from Kambakar, Dojong Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: so when he went to Tibet and he came back and met Khyentse Rinpoche and then Khyentse Rinpoche he went to Tibet and he came back to Nepal so they are having conversation with Khyentse Rinpoche and Rinpoche said how was your trip and all that
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Rinpoche asked him, did you give some, you know, empowerment when you went to Tibet?
[SPEAKER_00]: And Rinpoche was checking, did you give any of Long-Chin-Ying-Di-Ca-Pu?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, no, I didn't give because I didn't receive Long-Chin-Ying-Di-Ca-Pu.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then the conversation went on.
[SPEAKER_00]: He went back home.
[SPEAKER_00]: And next day, Khenpo Rinpoche sent his attendant to call him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he came and the Long-Chin-Ying-Di-Ca-Pu Wang was prepared for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: So special.
[SPEAKER_00]: So things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But of course, again, Rinpoche would not impose somebody who is not ready for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wouldn't say, they are all coming to receive my work.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he knows that you 100% trust him, he will take care of you 100% spiritually, and I think even worldly things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that seems like devotion you're talking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So when you have someone like that, who is like that, then somehow naturally you are drawn to it, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: So then you feel very strong devotion and you feel that this guy will never let you down or fool you or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I think that when we talk about devotion, it's an unreversible kind of irresistible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this, I think, eventually developed by spending time and being with him, being with someone like Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this sort of naturally comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it feels like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Devotion is a natural trust, a natural confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I think it's pretty much like trust.
[SPEAKER_00]: That someone will really, not only in this life, but will be able to guide you towards your...
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's a natural trust that's met with care.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think so, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you talked about the Dharma, you're talking about care.
[SPEAKER_01]: So a natural trust that's met with care.
[SPEAKER_01]: And a confidence, there's a type of confidence in the teacher as well, around this care.
[SPEAKER_00]: yes i think so i sometimes feel like you know when you fly somewhere you trust the captain yes that he will take you from place a to b you know and if you don't trust the captain then you don't feel comfortable yeah maybe don't get on the plane
[SPEAKER_00]: So I think Lama is similar, but not fly you, but I think guide you through his day and night.
[SPEAKER_01]: Guide you to awakening, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You mentioned that Rinpoche would often work on tamas that are not his.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're finishing the sadhanas or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was wondering, because our audience, we have varied audience, like Theravada practitioners and Zen practitioners and Tibetan practitioners.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was wondering if you could tell them a little bit about what a Dharma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dharma is, I think, Guru Rinpoche, 7th century.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he came to Tibet, many of the teachings that he brought to Tibet, and many of them he gave, transmitted himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is lineage which still exists in the Tibetan Buddhist tradition, especially in Nyingma tradition.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is known as Kama, oral lineage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now there are certain things that Guru Rinpoche maybe felt that maybe the time is not right or maybe it is more beneficial for the future generation or future.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he would hide them in different places, sometimes into the rocks, sometimes even into the sky.
[SPEAKER_00]: Varva.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many different places.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then when the time is right, when the dardana, or what we call the treasure revealer, when everything is ready then, sort of spontaneously, when all the, what we call temdala, the circumstances are right, sort of it reveals.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I was talking about Khyentse Rinpoche sort of knowing what we were doing So one time Khyentse Rinpoche was studying in India And Khyentse Rinpoche was in Nepal And I think Khyentse Rinpoche forgot to do the evening Dharmapala prayers And Khyentse Rinpoche would write a letter from Nepal to India saying don't stop Dharmapala, evening prayer Khyentse Rinpoche would jokingly say that the potatoes went to Nepal to come play
[SPEAKER_00]: So there are many cases like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somehow the close student, we always felt that Khyentse Rinpoche knew what we were doing and what's going on in our mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he would never sort of show that, you know, I know what you're thinking or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But somehow we always have the, know that he sort of knows.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one interesting incident was, there was an American monk who's been receiving teaching from Khyentse Rinpoche and all that, don't do much practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then Rinpoche told him, maybe you should do some retreat.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he built his retreat hut in Solukhumbu, Trishirin Rinpoche's monastery in Nepal.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he never stayed in the retreat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, he was hanging around.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Rinpoche said, your house is doing retreat.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are not doing retreat.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then he went back to do a retreat.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he was going to do retreat for three years originally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So after one year he got fed up.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, OK, now I'm going out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he prepared the talk and all this to finish his retreat.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that day he received the first letter in his life from Khyentse Rinpoche saying, I'm so proud of you doing three years retreat.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he went back into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he finished the attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: So many cases like that somehow happened.
[SPEAKER_00]: And especially the near end of Khyentse Rinpoche's life, he would sort of speak more, sort of more open about knowing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before he wouldn't really show so much.
[SPEAKER_00]: But later he would like, almost like he would act like you are in the same room.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when everything happens, He will just tell you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So one very interesting incident was, I was, Khyentse Rinpoche was in the palace of King of Bhutan, in Thimphu, on the second floor.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Rishi Rinpoche from Nepal arrived to Bhutan.
[SPEAKER_00]: So Khyentse Rinpoche told me to receive him.
[SPEAKER_00]: So since Sri Sri Rinpoche was my Vinaya teacher at that time, and then I brought him to the palace gate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So when we were entering the gate, Sri Sri Rinpoche quote from the, Sri Sri Rinpoche recite the quote from the Vinaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: So even the king's palace, what is there to be attached to it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So he was just reciting this to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we went up and we went to the second floor where Khyentse Rinpoche was.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when Tushar Rinpoche did prostration, first thing Khyentse Rinpoche said, you bhikshus, you galongs, always quote this word, then why do you come to the king's palace?
[SPEAKER_00]: So what was more amazing to me was that Tushar Rinpoche didn't, never surprised, didn't like something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then when we left the palace, I told Sri Sri Rinpoche, isn't it amazing Rinpoche knew right away what we were talking down there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Sri Sri Rinpoche is not surprised at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course he knows.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: That sort of teaches us.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even we said that we have faith or devotion, we still have a doubt that he is a human being.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: And from Sri Sri Rinpoche's perspective, Khyentse Rinpoche was like a Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it was nothing to be surprised.
[SPEAKER_00]: 100% devotion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So things like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You first came to America when?
[SPEAKER_01]: With Rinpoche?
[SPEAKER_01]: 1970.
[SPEAKER_00]: When Chayol Trungpa invited Khyentse Rinpoche, so one year after the Son has come up as visit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So mid-70s, 75.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mid-75.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you came with Khyentse Rinpoche and also it was on the invitation of Trungpa Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You must have been like 10 then or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What was your impression?
[SPEAKER_00]: Those days I'm just a kid, you know Enjoying coming to America I don't know much And I was quite fascinated with all the disciplines and kasungs and all those things Yes
[SPEAKER_00]: also one thing about Khyentse Rinpoche is that whenever he was invited to place like here or that time Rinpoche always tried to help whoever is inviting him he would never have his own like he could have started his center you know the many people were inspired by him but he would never do whichever invites he would go there and teach them whatever they request and then you just leave so therefore Rinpoche never started a center in the West
[SPEAKER_00]: So whenever there's a center who invites, Rinpoche will go there, teach, and then leave.
[SPEAKER_00]: So Rinpoche came to Western America many, many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: So always, whoever invites, he will just fulfill their wishes.
[SPEAKER_01]: For Rinpoche, it would be easy to create big centers here, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, if you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think Khyentse Rinpoche's main concern was to keep the lineages and the environments and transmissions and all those things to preserve in Nima and also all the four different schools.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that was his main concern.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess Khyentse Rinpoche and Trungpa Rinpoche had a close relationship as well, yeah?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I think very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think somehow Khyentse Rinpoche, even he lived in Shichen as a disciple of Shichen Gyatso Rinpoche, but somehow he had a lot of people from Surmang that had a strong devotion to Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also Trungpa Rinpoche was studying in Shetian at that time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Khenpo Kangshan is also from being from Shetian.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there's somehow a lot of connection from Tibet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did Khenpo Rinpoche teach in Soma at all?
[SPEAKER_00]: That I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I know Chögyam Trungpa used to come to Shichen.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also from Kambagar Monastery, there are many people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somehow we received some of the Khyentse Rinpoche's dharmas from Sulmanga and from Kambagar.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have kept it, the dharmas, some of the things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we received from... Khyentse Rinpoche's dharmas were kept in Namgyalse or Dutsitil?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's I don't know but some Surma monks brought it Surma monks, wow Brought it to Nepal and some the Shinje which I was talking about was sent down to Kambagar and they didn't finish proofreading so that's how it was left there So somehow the Rinpoche's connection with Surma and Kambagar and of course with other penshin and all the monasteries in Tibet So I think Tungpa Rinpoche and Khyentse Rinpoche had strong connection from Tibet
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there much connection between Sheshen Gompa and Soman Gompas?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think Gompa to Gompa, but from teacher to… Teacher to teacher?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, teacher to like Khenpo Kangshan, Sheshen Kongtul, all of them are Chögyam Thongpa's teachers.
[SPEAKER_00]: How interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then you came with Rinpoche to America in 1975.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you were quite young, eight years old then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it was more like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Fascinating.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then did you come regularly to the States?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever Khyentse Rinpoche came, I came.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think mainly we came three times.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the second time when Chögyam Trungpa Rinpoche was.
[SPEAKER_00]: enthroned as the, there was an enthronement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was it?
[SPEAKER_00]: As a, as a sakyong or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sakyong or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That, that.
[SPEAKER_01]: This came from, can't, can't say I remember, Che, did the ceremony.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was there, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were there, wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, and then the third time, the karmachilling, the cremation.
[SPEAKER_01]: This Sakyong ceremony, is it like what they do for kings, is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think there is a special kind of text or instruction in Rinchen Tenzu according to the Changdrei tradition.
[SPEAKER_00]: And based on that, I think Khyentse Rinpoche performed the ceremony.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Trungpa Rinpoche requested Khyentse Rinpoche to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He needed that wang.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they did a big ceremony.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then so you've seen Dharma change in like Tibetan Buddhism change In America over many years.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would seem do you have you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's your impression of how Dharma has changed in the West?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's call it the West.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I think When we first came many people don't know about Tibetan Buddhism, you know, that's 1970s people know more about Hare Krishna and
[SPEAKER_00]: So even when we're walking on the street with robes, people will go, hey, Hare Krishna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even sometimes at the airport, immigration, they say, oh, Khyentse Rinpoche was coming, and then they say, oh, big Hare Krishna is coming.
[SPEAKER_00]: So people don't know much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also the people who attend the, I think the Trungpa Rinpoche Sangha was different because they put on suit and tie, but other places where a lot of the hippies and, you know, those people would attend the teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I see the gradual changes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then now a lot of the, from the what we call mainstream, people like doctors, engineers, and especially I visit few times with His Holiness Dalai Lama's teaching, lots of scientists.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I think that whole transformation, transformation, yeah, I've seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the Dharma coming to the mainstream, science being interested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, and doctors and engineers.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now the Dharma is a very common use, widely used word.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could see that it's very much adapting to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: and then this I wouldn't imagine that seeing one two thousand Himalayans in New York in the one it was almost like being in Nepal yeah strong community here in New York
[SPEAKER_00]: before I think when you see one Tibetan in the street like wow seeing an alien Khenpo Rinpoche went to World Trade Center that time the Twin Tower and then Rinpoche went upstairs and there was a kamatini was up there and there was a big surprise kamatini from Canada and then Khenpo Rinpoche was invited to Canada gave teaching there
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you wouldn't think you would meet there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you think that the Dharma, I'm interested in your thoughts on how the Dharma is coming to the West and whether you think it's doing well.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you come to America, what do you think is, what are you teaching and why?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think Dhamma is like, I don't know whether the word right or not, but getting rooted in the West.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before it was a little bit like I said, it's kind of exotic, Asian.
[SPEAKER_00]: you know some kind of thing but now it's sort of becoming a main yeah becoming heavy kind of serious study and also with the science and all that i think it will also benefit even without the the labeling of the being a buddhist you know they're using the buddhist idea of loving kindness and compassion into the mainstream so i think it will continue and benefit a lot of people
[SPEAKER_00]: And mainly I came because the Himalayan group here, they want to do the Paranirvana of Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's nice to come because every time I come here, I meet some people saying that, oh, I know you from eight years old.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wherever I go.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also being Khyentse Rinpoche's, Khyentse Rinpoche's student,
[SPEAKER_00]: I could go anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: I feel that kind of, I can feel it like a home.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somehow some connection is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I meet any Sangha member of Chögyam Trungpa, there's a strong connection with Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Sangha member from any other schools, somehow there's some connection with Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: So don't feel like stranger or anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Big family.
[SPEAKER_01]: Khyentse Rinpoche have big family, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also from different schools, you know, like Pernod Rinpoche students, or nowadays there are a lot of Pernod Rinpoche students, Meanderling students.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somehow we all feel, some of them I met yesterday, some ex-moms from Meanderling that we received Rinpoche Tenshi together, some from Pernod Rinpoche who received the Nyingma Kama together.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somewhere, everywhere there's somehow some connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't feel like you're strangers anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: And do you feel a responsibility?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, do you feel like a responsibility to help support Kensei Rinpoche's work continuing into the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that a heavy responsibility or how do you feel about that?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think it's a heavy thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, well, if I look at my life, of course, I wouldn't be able to serve Rinpoche, but I've been with Rinpoche since I was five.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then when I was like 15 or something, then I started to serve Rinpoche a little bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still a very distracted young man.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I was 25 years, Kenzo Rinpoche passed away.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then that time I was a little bit struggling to continue with the monastery works and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But somehow with Rinpoche's blessing, everything sort of falls into place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Yangtze, Khyentse Rinpoche Yangtze was recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I served him for 20 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: time goes so fast that's amazing yes 20 years I spent so I spent 20 years with previous Khyentse Rinpoche and 20 years with young Khyentse Rinpoche and between five years sort of little bit finding the reincarnation all this kind of thing
[SPEAKER_00]: And then by 2010, I wanted to put a little bit more into practice because I received so much teaching and blessing from Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: But somehow, Khyentse Rinpoche made me the chairman of the Nyingma Meulam in India.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I couldn't do retreat for three more years.
[SPEAKER_00]: So just after third year of the responsibility of Nyingma Meulam, then I went into retreat for maybe three and a half or four years.
[SPEAKER_00]: so my my hope is that to do every year at least if I can hundred days of retreat which cancer measure recommends yeah and then I'm not worried or don't feel pressure because I think when the time is right everything somehow falls into by itself blessings and when the time is right people just
[SPEAKER_00]: People like, just showed up, Lama showed up to help me translate Rinpoche's teachings and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, things would just come naturally.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the tendril.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Never met Rinpoche, but somehow, very strong devotion, connection with Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he is there to help me.
[SPEAKER_00]: which is Dharma practice introduced in the West.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we have finished for 10 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: 13 years of translating.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these projects are such long-term projects, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: All the projects in Dharma, you have to think long-term.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even for you, you served Khyentse Rinpoche for 20 years and then Khyentse Yangtze for 20 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a surprise.
[SPEAKER_01]: You said 20 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Time is going.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, very fast.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then now my main kind of thing that I want to do is that I transmit the lineage back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So many I received, and especially in Tibet.
[SPEAKER_00]: In Tibet as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: In Tibet.
[SPEAKER_00]: A few years ago I went.
[SPEAKER_00]: I gave as much as I can.
[SPEAKER_00]: The next day I arrived, the next day I started teaching until the day I left.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I got a very short time permit to stay, but as much as I can from morning till evening.
[SPEAKER_00]: I tried, especially I want to transmit the lungs.
[SPEAKER_00]: For Wang, I'm not sure whether I'm qualified or not, but somehow people like Wang.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I want to give the lungs.
[SPEAKER_00]: This year, I tried to go, give me Pham Kham Mung, but I didn't get permission.
[SPEAKER_01]: You got Jigme Lingpa Sambung in Nepal?
[SPEAKER_01]: In Nepal, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was quite amazing because I was very happy that a lot of people came from all over the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And on the internet as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it was cancer, which is lineage.
[SPEAKER_00]: So many people, they came.
[SPEAKER_00]: and I'm able to give them and then after the transmission everybody fly back to their own kind of you know home and they will continue with spreading so that's very very beautiful I feel very satisfied very satisfied with that a lot of a lot of people turned out I think the biggest ever in Sheshet Monastery you were both there right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nepal yes about six ten thousand people about 650 Lama Turku Khyambus only amazing and from the all the four different schools
[SPEAKER_01]: And also it was on the internet, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: They showed some.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, for Facebook and all those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, the transmission, I think... Has to be personal.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think so, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is my hope, to practice a little bit and then give transmission.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you mind telling us a little bit about the previous Sheshen Ravichand?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are what number?
[SPEAKER_00]: Seventh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seventh, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know much about the previous Chechen Ramja Rinpoche, but Khyentse Rinpoche was more close with Chechen Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sixth Chechen Ramja Rinpoche considered as one of his teachers, but his main teacher was Chechen Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if you sort of look in the lineage ways, general, from Longchenpa to Jimmy Lingpa, Jimmy Lingpa to Khyentse Wangpo, the Khyentse Wangpo's
[SPEAKER_00]: one of the main students was Mekong Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Mekong Rinpoche sort of hand over all his unfinished work to Shisheng Gyaltsab.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Gyaltsab's like heart-son was Bibistonse Kense Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somehow that how the lineage is very direct, I feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I feel that's very important too.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were a tuku of Sheshan Khyentsev as well, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is some, there is a little bit of a story that maybe I can tell you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That in Khyentse Rinpoche's dream, I was recognized by Karmapa, so I'll tell you the secret also.
[SPEAKER_00]: Khyentse Rinpoche went, after Karmapa told him that, Khyentse Rinpoche one time went to Nama Buddha and he had a dream of the three main masters of Sheshan, Khyentse Rinpoche, Ramchandra Rinpoche and Kongtrul Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they had some exchange discussions through some kind of poem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And mainly Rinpoche was saying that he felt very sad that you all died in the Cultural Revolution in Tibet.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somehow they all sort of merge into one and dissolve into kind of being a reincarnation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then the Karmapa and Khyentse Rinpoche and Chojulingpa in Rumtheg, they had a discussion, what to name me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Khyentse Rinpoche wanted to give me the name of Sheshen Khyentse because he was more close to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Chojol Lingpa asked, who is the most important Lama from Sheshen?
[SPEAKER_00]: And Chojol Lingpa said, that's Sheshen Ramja.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then Chojol Lingpa said, okay, if there's a choice, let's go for the highest.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then,
[SPEAKER_00]: My grandmother later told Ujjain Dhamcharambache, don't tell this story.
[SPEAKER_00]: The people will say that Khyentse Dhamcharambache made his own nephew a tukku.
[SPEAKER_00]: So just leave it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Karmapa did it.
[SPEAKER_00]: His own grandson.
[SPEAKER_00]: His own grandson as a tukku.
[SPEAKER_00]: So just don't talk about this thing because people cannot accept these days, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: They make rumors.
[SPEAKER_00]: So just leave it, Karmapa.
[SPEAKER_00]: So somehow they're all three involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So just now, my name is Ram Jam, successor of Sheshan Ram Jam.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so the previous, Sheshan Gil Sab was a teacher of Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, teacher of Khyentse Rinpoche and direct student of Mipham Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: A direct student of Mipham Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: Amazing.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is amazing, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: And unfinished Mipham Rinpoche's works as hand robot.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he has that responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's quite a responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So did Khyentse Rinpoche tell you any stories about Sheshen Gyatsov that you remember?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, he would never even name, call Sheshen Gyatsov.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would just say the kindness one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: So when he says kindness one, it's Sheshen Gyatsov.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've never seen Khyentse Rinpoche cry except when visiting the Sheshen Gyatsov's retreat when we were in Tibet.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm very, very close.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now you're concentrating on doing retreat and passing on the lungs.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then I enjoy myself sometimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything else you want to share?
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to be conscious of your time as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think one thing, maybe one unique quality of Khyentse Rinpoche is, like I said, non-sectarian.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you will find students from all the different schools.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like Khyentse Rinpoche, according to him, belongs to a Khajiit tradition.
[SPEAKER_00]: But somehow he feels very close with Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then any other Lamas from different schools, somehow they feel they are like students of Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even from the Samtruku, from the Gelug tradition, they would say, oh my teacher is from Khyentse Rinpoche, but I am Gelugpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: And some people from Gajju tradition say, oh my teacher is from Khyentse Rinpoche, but I am Gajjupa.
[SPEAKER_00]: This thing I don't see so much in these days with other Lamas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either you follow him and be his lineage, you can't be from a different lineage and be his student.
[SPEAKER_00]: This, I think, is like one unique quality of being a real spiritual releme master.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one, even I found, after Khyentse Rinpoche passed away, one letter he wrote to a pen practitioner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: and teaching him how to practice according to burn.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this kind of openness is something very special quality of Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he was a teacher across traditions and he can really influence people, but they didn't feel like they then had to become Nyingma or from Xie Xian, this type of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think this is an important point because when you read the Namtas of the great masters,
[SPEAKER_01]: You see that they had many teachers from many different traditions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Khyentse Rinpoche had 50 different teachers from all the different schools.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: And three men from Gelug, I think the 14th Dalai Lama, in the number eight pension, and one Gelug Geshe from Amdo.
[SPEAKER_00]: One, actually, the Gelung Geshe, he's the one who predicted that Khyentse Rinpoche's Dharma activity will cover the one third of the world or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: One third of the world?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I think this is coming true, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then also, if you look at his Holiness Dalai Lama, Khyentse Rinpoche was a teacher to his Holiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: His Holiness Dalai Lama mentioned once, I heard in Drepung, that he really learned how the Rime is practiced from Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so these great masters can draw from the great teachers no matter what tradition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And does this extend like even into like the secular world, like teaching scientists, teaching... Because nowadays, you know, mindfulness is very prominent in the West.
[SPEAKER_01]: I haven't fully formed the question, but people are learning mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But normally we talk about view, meditation and conduct.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so do you think when they're just, the mindfulness is so popular, is it, it seems to be missing view, but is that okay?
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness maybe can act like a door to a dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, people get more interested in mindfulness and somehow it benefits them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then they get more interested to go into deeper practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So because people a little bit hesitation with religion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's not mindfulness can be like yoga was at one point very popular and many people through yoga they somehow get deeper into practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I think whatever benefits beings I think that is the manifestation of Buddha Dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I think the mindfulness can become a door.
[SPEAKER_00]: We cannot say the mindfulness is the ultimate practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it can be like a door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then those from which then people who want to go deeper into practice, then I'm sure then they will have the full practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what if someone is doing meditation, mindfulness, what is their next step if they want to go deeper and enter one of those doors?
[SPEAKER_00]: So I think once they get into the kind of, let's say, the taste of the mindfulness, then I think they will have to really get into serious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Normally, mindfulness is more like a shinai, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: More like a shamatha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So shamatha can always be like a door.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if they want to get deeper into it, then they'll have to take refuge in, you know, start from the control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So finding a teacher is important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Finding a teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, thank you so much for joining us and being so generous with your time, but also so generous with your stories.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's very precious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So wonderful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next on the Wisdom Podcast, I speak with Tara Brach, American psychologist, renowned meditation teacher, and author of many books, including the bestseller, Radical Acceptance, Embracing Your Life with the Heart of a Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tara is widely celebrated for her pioneering work combining Western psychology and Eastern spiritual practices.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it comes from science, Daniel.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like there's so much research now on the difference between states and traits that
[SPEAKER_01]: And if we touch after we nurture, this is generally, there's some more spaciousness and tenderness, but if we rush right on, we don't end up getting familiar in a way that we have more access to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what neuroscience is showing
[SPEAKER_01]: If we have a negative experience, it's very sticky and it stays in our unconscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Positive ones, not so much.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that thing that Rick Hansen always says is that, you know, we're Velcro for negative experiences and Teflon for the positive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, to get the...
[SPEAKER_01]: liberating experiences to have a little more of that stickiness, we need to stay in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: On purpose, notice what they're like, rest in them, let go into them even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that actually, what we discover is that that experience during After the Rain is more the truth of who we are than any story we've ever told about ourselves.